<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The destruction and sacke cruelly committed by the Duke of Guyse and his company, in the towne of Vassy, the fyrste of Marche, in the yeare M. D. LXII.</title>
            <title>Destruction du saccagement, exerce cruellement par le Duc de Guise en la ville de Vassy. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1562</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01198</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11312</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112679</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847925</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847925</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12993</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01198)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12993)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 241:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The destruction and sacke cruelly committed by the Duke of Guyse and his company, in the towne of Vassy, the fyrste of Marche, in the yeare M. D. LXII.</title>
                  <title>Destruction du saccagement, exerce cruellement par le Duc de Guise en la ville de Vassy. English.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Henry Sutton for Edvvarde Sutton dvvellyng in Lumbard strete at the signe of the cradell. The fyrst day of May,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1562]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Destruction du saccagement, exerce cruellement par le Duc de Guise en la ville de Vassy.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Great crueltie done by the duke of Guyse at Vassy.</note>
                  <note>Last leaf blank.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Guise, François de Lorraine, --  duc de, 1519-1563.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Wars of the Huguenots, 1562-1598 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12993:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 78 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:12993:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 78 -->
            <p>The Deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſacke cruelly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by the Duke of Guyſe and his company, in the towne of Vaſſy, the fyrſte of Marche, in the yeare <hi>M.D.LXII.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IMPRINTED AT LONDON BY HENRY SVTTON for Edvvarde Sutton dvvellyng in Lumbard ſtrete at the ſigne of the cradell.</p>
            <p>The fyrſt day of May.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:12993:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 79 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:12993:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 79 -->
            <head>
               <hi>THE DESTRVCTION</hi> and ſacke cruelly committed by the duke of Guyſe and his company in the towne of Vaſſye the firſte day of Marche. <hi>1562.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aterdaye beynge the laſt day of Februarie, the duke of Guyſe lay at Da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>martin ſe frank to the which it is two leagues from Iainuille, and from the ſaid Dammartin to Vaſſy are other two leagues, both the which make foure leagues diſtaunce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the ſayd Iainuille (wher is the ſayde dukes houſe and reſtyng place) and the ſaid Vaſſy.</p>
            <p>Sondaye the fyrſte of Marche the ſaid duke departed from Dam martyn aforeſayde, accompanied with .ii. hundred horſe at the leaſt, euery horſe man of them, hauynge two or thre piſtolets, and many of
<pb facs="tcp:12993:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 80 -->theim hauyng long harquebuſes.</p>
            <p>The ſayd duke of Guyſe fayned he wold the ſtraight way to Eſcla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, without commyng to Vaſſy: And thereof was made a greate bruite before he diſloged, he paſſed by Brouſſell, a village neere to the ſaid Vaſſy, within one quarter of a league. And at that time thei rang to a ſermon in the reformed church of the ſaid Vaſſy. Wherevppon the duke and his companye tooke oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to ſay and aſke, what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth this ryngyng?</p>
            <p>Wherevnto it was aunſwered by many of the Dukes band and ſom others of the ſayd towne of Vaſſy, it is to the ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Hugenots. Whervpon they could not poſſibly ſo colour and diſſemble the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier, but there eſcaped oute of the mouths of the moſt honorable and reſpected perſons among them: yea
<pb facs="tcp:12993:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 80 -->and others of meaner degree, theſe woordes folowynge, By Goddes deathe we will Hugenote them by and by of an other faſhion.</p>
            <p>Others, that wer of the baſeſt ſort as pages, ſeruantes, and lackays, ſwearyng alſo Gods deathe, ſayd, Will they not geue vs the ſpoyle<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And as ſone as that talke was en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded, the ſayd Duke and his troupe drew towards the ſayd Vaſſy, &amp; ſo beyng well appointed, entred into the abbey, and made his horſe and the horſes of the beſte to be helden in hand, without that any of them were put into the ſtable.</p>
            <p>The ſaid duke beyng within the monaſterie acompanied and waye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted on by the Priour of the ſayde Vaſſy, called de Salles, hauynge after them a no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre of pages &amp; lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keys, with long harquebuſes, pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolets, and their gauntlets, taried
<pb facs="tcp:12993:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 81 -->there a verye lytle whyle. For hee could not conteine, ſo long thought he the time til he might execute his former determyned intente, as it is eaſie to ſe and iudge. And being there (becauſe his deuocion myght be ſeene) he toke onely a lytle holly water, and after went foorth with his great company.</p>
            <p>Within the market place of the ſayd towne were .xl. men of armes and archers, of the company which were the ordinary garriſon there. Who had put them ſelues therein, and walked vp and downe wel ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and had taried the dukes com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ming all that morninge.</p>
            <p>The ſayde men of armes and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers ioyned with him, namely the head of them, yong Broſſe, the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of the Lord of Broſſe, marching in order to fight. And wente ſtraighte
<pb facs="tcp:12993:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 81 -->to the place where thoſe of the ſayd Churche and reformed Relygion made their preaching. Which was in a barne that they had made fit for that purpoſe, beynge dyſtante from the Monaſtery aboute one hundred paſes.</p>
            <p>And commynge to the place they found the wicket open, which wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſawe, they cauſed the ſayde la Broſſe the yonger, to enter firſte hauinge .vii. men of armes wyth hym. And hauynge conſidered the Minyſter and the people aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, whyche were aboute twelue hundred perſons, it was ſayd vnto them by ſome of the Churche, my mayſters, If it pleaſe you, take a rome. Wherevnto for anſwere the firſte worde they vſed was this, Goddes death lette vs kyll them all.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12993:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 82 -->
And hauyng ſo ſayd, woulde haue gone out, and in dede ſome of them wente foorth, while the reſt taried within: becauſe the people vppon this threatnyng ſent to the doore, thinkyng to ſhutte it vppon them, knowyng there was ſome buſines toward, &amp; that they were in greate danger, for than they perceiued the duke of Guyſe in armes.</p>
            <p>Which thyng the ſayde Duke per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuyng, with his people preſented them the harquebouſe and piſtolet, and ſhot thorow the reherſed wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kette of the barne, whyche was yet open, and ſo were the next vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the doore ſtaine &amp; hurt: and ther by the ſame forſaken, &amp; conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thaſſemble deliuered to the pray</p>
            <p>Then entred in the Duke, with many others, ſhootyng mightilye at the thickeſt aſſemble of all the people, and ſtewe and hurt a great
<pb facs="tcp:12993:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 82 -->numbre. That doone they wente vppon theim with greate ſlices of ſwordes and curtalaces, and hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out the poore men, the women, and children. and when they were out: of neceſſitie thei muſt paſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt two rankes, as well of men of armes, as of others of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, and euen thorowe the myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt betwene bothe, as it were tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe a lane, or an alley of a great lengthe. And in paſſyng, euery one of them ſtrake at them with great blowes of curtilace and ſwoorde, in ſuche ſorte as manye of theim wente not farre, but felle downe ſtarke deade.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtandyng ſome one eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, one ſorte beyng hurt, ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnhurte: but immediatly they were rencountred with an other troupe of the companie which ſlew and hurte with as muche crueltie
<pb facs="tcp:12993:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 83 -->as the others, and that as much as in them laye.</p>
            <p>Thoſe which gat vp to the toppe of the barne ſekinge all meanes to ſaue them ſelues were ſhotte at, and ouertaken with ſhotte of har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quebouſe, wherby many were ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and fell downe dead to the grounde, whyche was an horrible ſighte and a dredfull, the ſame en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duringe before it ceaſſed one houre and a halfe.</p>
            <p>After this were the trumpettes blowen vp in ſigne of victorye and triumphe, after whiche ſoundyng, yet they withdrew not them ſelues in halfe an houre more. Ther died within the barn .xii. men, wemen, and Children, and manye others that paſſed thorowe the rankes with ſome that gotte as farre as theyr houſes. And there dieth day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the nomber of the hurt, which
<pb facs="tcp:12993:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 83 -->is greate.</p>
            <p>The houſe of one called Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, whyche was nexte to the ſayde church was ſacked and rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, whyle there was one napkyn lefte, thoccaſion was that it was ſayd there was armour and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon therein.</p>
            <p>The ſayd Duke toke and led a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye the miniſter being ſore wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and alſo the Captayne of the ſayd towne of Vaſſy with certaine others of the towne for pryſoners: and after that went to dinner to a village called Alanccourt, &amp; whan hee had dyned, wente to bedde to Eſclaron.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the ſayde Miniſter was vnable to ſit on horſebacke by reaſon of hys woundes, whyche were not dreſſed, he was caryed by foure men vppon a barrowe vnto the ſayde Eſclaron.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12993:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 84 -->
And or euer the Duke departed Vaſſy, before he came oute of the churche, the wyfe of a man called Nicholas la Vauſſe, an honeſte merchant who was ſore hurt, and mynded to go to her houſe, ſaw her ſonne in paſſyng thorow the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket place, whoſe bodye one ranne thorowe with a ſworde, wherwith ſhe beyng moued, hyed her, thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng for pitie to ſaue hym, but ſhe ſo lyttle preuayled, as a horſeman ran at her, and after he had thruſt her thorow with his ſworde, tooke from her her purſe and girdle with other thyngs ſhe had, and gat hym agayne to horſe.</p>
            <p>The tewſday folowing were bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried .xlv. flayne perſons, and there remaineth hurt .iiii. ſcore or a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, whereof a greate parte were out of all hope of lyfe.</p>
            <p>Thus may ye in a maner behold
<pb facs="tcp:12993:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 84 -->the full diſcourſe of this vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralneſſe, crueltie, and murder, that the ſayde Duke of Guyſe hath committed againſt the ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iectes of the Frenche Kyng his ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
